Today's דף Daf is מ"ז Mem Zayin and we actually are more
or less caught up. We pick up on the bottom of מ"ו
עמוד ב'. Mem Vav Amud Beis.
המוכר עצמו ובניו לעובדי כוכבים, Hamocher Atzmo u'vanav l'ovdei kochavim, the משנה
Mishna about eight lines from the bottom. המוכר עצמו ובניו לעובדי כוכבים.
Hamocher Atzmo u'vanav l'ovdei kochavim. So we've been dealing with slaves and
freeing slaves and other types of תיקון עולם Tikkun Olam but this
has definitely been a dominant theme here around slaves although the last
two משניות Mishnayos were around issues about actually getting us back to
marriage and divorce and other תיקון עולם Tikkun Olam related to that.
But now anyway we are one of the things we've also introduced
was slaves and then redeeming captives and now we have a scenario
where you yourself are selling yourself as a slave out of poverty
obviously it must be some serious situation of abject poverty and it's
about other people redeeming you. So it's interesting how those sort of
previous themes are converging. So somebody sells himself and his children לעובדי
כוכבים l'ovdei kochavim to non-Jews into some type of servitude. You know
is it forever? Is it slave is it actual as slaves? Is
it indentured servants? But clearly not an ideal situation and you don't
have the free choice to leave. You have to be redeemed and
somebody has to buy you back. So אין פודין אותו. Ein podin
oso. We don't redeem this person. Okay so after telling us that
we don't pay back for redeeming slaves more than their value here's
somebody that we don't redeem because they sold he sold himself. Now
it doesn't seem like that there's the only person the only problem
we could be seen as correcting here it's not like somebody came
and seized people as captives and we don't want to encourage that
behavior. There's only one behavior we want to encourage here which is
sell yourself right? You sold yourself. If you know that people will
feel a need of פדיון שבויים Pidyon Shvuyim we have to come
and redeem you and so on then it'll make it that much
easier for you to make this decision that you never should be
making. So it seems very harsh right? But we've had dealt with
harsh issues. Somebody divorces his wife under certain circumstances he has to
know he's not he's not remarrying her. Right? So somebody sells himself
he has to know that that's not going to be easy to
reverse. So you could say that's completely terrible like you know you're
leaving him in the hands of the non-Jews he's going to be
מחלל שבת Mechallel Shabbos he's going to eat טריפות Treifos he's not
going to be part of the Jewish community. You know it comes
to these like difficult decisions of do you allow individual cases that
you're not dealing with in order so that you don't open up
the floodgates and create just encourage that behavior and make it much
more widespread? You know
I got to tell you I have this experience of maybe it's
a completely
of much different proportions but you know there's a גמרא Gemara that
basically says that if somebody, I think it's about שמע Shema though
it might be about דאווענינג Davening but I think it's about שמע.
Shema. If somebody says שמע Shema and they didn't have כוונה Kavana
he should go ahead and say it again. So the גמרא Gemara
says no how can you not have had כוונה? Kavana? Like you
know that's completely unconscionable. You don't say it again and like you
you smack the guy up I mean figuratively for not having כוונה
Kavana the first time. You know but but you don't say it
again right? So you'd say how could I not say it again?
Right? I didn't have כוונה Kavana I gotta be יוצא. Yotzei. But
if you feel like I can always go back and say it
again right then the next then the next time you're not you
know you're not going to be as מקפיד Makpid of having that
כוונה. Kavana. Well if I didn't have enough כוונה Kavana I can
always go back and say it again. Right? So if you tell
me no you're not allowed to repeat and that's not the הלכה
Halacha you are allowed but I'm saying but if you take the
position you're not allowed to repeat it right? You're going to the
problem's going to occur a lot less frequently right? So if it
seems like harsh decisions right
but there's I mean that's it's funny when you think about תיקון
עולם Tikkun Olam is not all like it's not all like you
know roses and chocolate right? תיקון עולם Tikkun Olam sometimes means making
like hard decisions about about immediate suffering in order to address deeper
systemic problems or to not allow for systemic problems to develop. Yes.
What about the part that community might be responsible for this person
having done that?
In other words what's their responsibility in this? You mean what how
did they let him to get to this state of poverty? Right
that's an interesting question yeah I don't know I don't know how
to answer that. Yes sometimes in terms of maybe I understand that
in those situations maybe if they have a real immediate sense of
responsibility then that creates maybe a real immediate obligation to redeem. Right
that's a interesting point yeah. I mean this is an issue that's
come up recently when someone is responsible themselves responsible for them being
taken captive or something like that. Right how much do the other
people have to feel the need to right? We've had the case
of those Iranian Americans who were stuck in Iran because they were
stupid enough to go there. Right right right. So alright so anyway
but here it's a problem not just of a one-time event hey
you brought it upon yourself here it's a much bigger issue. Like
okay people sometimes do stupid things and you know but then it's
a really terrible situation we have to help them with. Here the
issue is is that if we go ahead and redeem them it's
going to make it that much easier for the next person. just
to sell himself, or for this person to sell himself again, knowing
that the community will feel responsible. So there's a much deeper, larger
societal issue going on here. המוכר עצמו ובניו לעובדי כוכבים אין פודין
אותו, Hamocher atzmo uvanav le’ovdei chochavim ein podin oto, you don't redeem
him. אבל פודין את הבנים לאחר מיתת אביהם, Aval podin et habanim
le’achar mitat avihem, but it wasn't the kids' fault, so once the
father dies, you redeem the kids. Now, why do you wait till
the father dies? So, it's going to seem possibly in the גמרא,
Gemara, well, maybe as long as the father's alive he can help
protect them, but then after he's dead and he can't protect them
anymore, creates a heightened responsibility. Or it could also be the same
idea, which is that as long as the father's alive, if we
redeem the kids, I'll figure, okay, so it's not going to be
so bad for me to sell my kids off, I know at
least they'll be redeemed. Okay, but if it's not going to happen
in your lifetime, then it makes, you know, it's that much harsher,
that much consequence that you're making this decision. אמר רב אסי: Amar
Rav Assi: והוא שמכר ושנה ושילש. V’hu shemachar v’shana v’shilesh. So the
גמרא Gemara immediately pulls back on this. That's a little too harsh.
We would not say that in every situation. Okay, if somebody—it's repeated
behavior. He's done it once and twice and three times, right? So
that's like the whole חזקה. Chazakah. By the third time we're not
going to redeem you anymore. But it's—again, what's fascinating is this push
and pull, this dynamic between, right, addressing larger societal concerns about the
future implications and dealing with immediate problems.
Okay, and immediate suffering. Now, הנהו בני בי מכסי, Hanehu benei Bei
Michsi, there were people from this city of מכסי, Michsi, דיזפי זוזי
מעובדי כוכבים, D’yazpi zuzei me’ovdei chochavim, they borrowed money from non-Jews, ולא
הוה להו למיפרעיהו, V’lo hava lehu lemifre’eihu, and they didn't have enough
money to pay them back. אתו וקא גרדי להו. Atu v’ka gardi
lehu. So the non-Jews came and they seized the people themselves as
payment of their loans. You know, they basically took them off as
slaves, or at least for a period of time. אתו לקמיה דרב
הונא, Atu l’kamei d’Rav Huna, so they came in front of—it seems
like whether the captives themselves had a certain degree of freedom, right?
They were like, you know, they were slaves, but they had freedom
of movement. So they came to רב הונא Rav Huna and they
said, like, could you please get the community to redeem us? Now,
this is also interesting because they didn't make the choice to sell
themselves as slaves. This was more negligent than it was intentional, right?
They were borrowing money, they didn't have money to pay back. They
might have known that that would have been the consequence of not
paying back, right? But it was—there was at least—it might have been
a large degree of negligence. I mean, also if you don't have
money, what's negligence, right? My crops are failing. I mean, how negligent
could I be? But maybe don't borrow money from people that you
know are going to seize you as slaves. You know, so there
was negligence here, but it wasn't intentional. Anyway, they came to רב
הונא, Rav Huna, אמר להו מאי אעביד לכו, Amar lehu mai a’avid
lachu, hey, what can I do for you? I can't help you.
דתנן המוכר עצמו ובניו לעובדי כוכבים אין פודין אותו, Detnan hamocher atzmo
uvanav le’ovdei chochavim ein podin oto, we don't redeem them. אמר ליה
רב אבא למידתנו רבינו, Amar lei Rav Abba limadtenu Rabbeinu, and רב
אבא Rav Abba said to רב הונא, Rav Huna, but our Master,
you have taught us, והוא שמכר ושנה ושילש, V’hu shemachar v’shana v’shilesh,
so we had it before by רב אסי, Rav Assi, but apparently
רב הונא Rav Huna also taught this, that it's only somebody who
did it once, twice, and three
times. אמר ליה הני מרגא רגילי דעבדי הכי. Amar lei hani Marga
regili d’avdi hachi. No, these people are accustomed to doing this. Okay,
so basically this is a case where they're accustomed. Now, what did
that mean? Did that mean that this had happened to them two
or three times, that they had been seized? Or were they accustomed
to borrowing from these people, you know,
and jeopardizing the fact that they might have been seized? You know,
it sounds like if it was just—okay, that's true, you know, they
actually had been seized two or three times and this was the
third time already that they had to be brought back, then it's
not such a חידוש, Chidush, it's just an illustration. Again, one wonders
how much, you know, this is—there is a חידוש Chidush here, wasn't
intentional, it was negligent, and how much is it the pattern of
the behavior, even if it didn't actually translate into having been taken
as a slave and brought back two or three times. Maybe this
sort of negligent pattern of behavior is sufficient? That remains a little
unclear from the גמרא. Gemara. Okay, so let's take a look, another
case. ההוא גברא דזבין נפשיה ללודאי. Hahu gavra d’zavin nafshie l’Luda’ei. A
certain person sold himself to the לודאי. Luda’ei. Now, who are these
לודאי? Luda’ei? So, Lydians maybe is—maybe it's a name of a place.
But you look at רש״י, Rashi, he says, אומה שאוכלין בני אדם,
Umah she’ochlin benei adam, cannibals. Now, we're going to see why, because
obviously this was some very dangerous situation to be with the לודאי.
Luda’ei. Now, if you take a look, though, at Soncino, people, because
Soncino, the English translation is so stilted, I mean, whatever, nobody uses
Soncino anymore, but—but it has great footnotes. And if you look at
Soncino, I was alerted to this while שמואל הרצפלד Shmuel Herzfeld told
me about this in the name of Daniel Boyarin, and then I
checked the Soncino and the Soncino had said it. Are you telling
me Daniel Boyarin uses the Soncino? No. Anyway, here's
the Soncino. Luderi, Ludi, people who arrange and hire men for gladiatorial
contests, because the Ludi means for games. So people who hire men
for gladiatorial contests to kill off with the finishing stroke the enraged
beasts. Viz, Gretz, etc., Krauss, etc. So the classic, these, you know,
these real—these some of these early
dictionaries of Aramaic, you know, very academic ones, ones that we don't
use so much
because Jastrow says the same thing. He also says next to Rebbe
saying that this was a group that did human sacrifices in their
religion. Okay so it's clear obviously when you're in... It's clear obviously
your life is at risk when you're in these people's hands, okay?
But mostly, it seems the best translation here is these gladiators. Okay,
so anyway he- they sold themselves to these people. So אתו לקמיה
דרבי אמי, Atu lekamei d'Rabbi Ami, so people came to Rabbi Ami.
I'm sorry, they came to Rabbi Ami. אמרו ליה, Amru leih, they
said to him, פרקין, Pirkin, redeem us. אמר ליה, Amar leih, תנן,
Tnan, המוכר את עצמו ואת בניו ללודים אין פודין אותו אבל פודין
את הבנים, hamocher et atzmo v'et banav l'Ludim ein podin oto aval
podin et habanim, משום קלקולא. mishum kilkula.
So he's going to say now here's why we do have to
save you. Okay even though and maybe of course the funny thing
is, it didn't say it was two or three times, that right,
that might have been, are we still working with that parameter? It's
only two or three times? But anyway, he creates even a greater
sense of mandate to save them. Why? Because why do we redeem
the children? So he says the reason we redeem the children, you
could have said they're not at fault, but he says the reason
we redeem the children is משום קלקולא. mishum kilkula. If the father
is dead and no longer around to protect them, then they can
be abused, you know, sexual abuse, right? So therefore that's why there's
a heightened responsibility. Okay, he's not reading it that it wasn't their
fault, but that's why because when there's a real high degree of
risk of life or of, you know, personal safety to the person,
we redeem regardless. וכל שכן הכא דאיכא קטלא, V'chol shekein hacha d'ika
katla, all the more so here where you're dealing with issues of
life and death, of murder, right? So they'll murder you, you know,
human sacrifice, cannibals, or most likely you're going to be in the
gladiatorial games. Certainly we have a responsibility to redeem you. So אמרו
ליה רבנן לרבי אמי, Amru leih rabanan l'Rabbi Ami, so the rabbis
said to Rabbi Ami, והאי ישראל מומר הוא דחזי ליה דקאכיל נבילות
וטריפות. v'hai Yisrael mumar hu d'chazi leih d'kachil neveilot u'treifot.
We don't have a responsibility to these people. They are מומרים, mumarim,
they've basically abandoned the faith because we see that they eat טריפות.
treifot. Now where were they eating טריפות? treifot? When they were with
the gladiators? I mean, you know, how much choice did they have?
Okay, well we don't have a responsibility to these people. They're not
פרום. frum. They've abandoned the faith, okay? So אמר להו, Amar lehu,
he said to them, אימא לתיאבון הוא דקאכיל. eima l'teiavon hu d'kachil.
Maybe they're doing it out of lust and appetite, not out of
like, you know, and that could just mean that's the food that
they're fed. So rather than saying I'm going to just eat the
vegetables, right, which was not seen as a real option in those
days, which you know, okay, they eat it because they're given meat
and they're not so פרום frum that they don't insist that they
don't refuse to eat it. But it doesn't mean they're מומר לתיאבון.
mumar l'teiavon. It doesn't mean they're מומר להכעיס. mumar l'hachis. It doesn't
mean that they've really abandoned the faith. It's just they're not able
to be that פרום, frum, you know, under those circumstances. So the
גמרא Gemara says, אמרו ליה, Amru leih,
they said to him, וזימנין דאיכא היתירא ואיסורא קמיה ושביק היתירא ואכיל
איסורא. v'zimnin d'ika heteira v'issura kamei v'shavik heteira v'achil issura. No, we
have seen that there are times when they're presented both kosher and
non-kosher food at the same time
and they just abandon the kosher food and they go, you know,
they go for the lobster and for the and for the ham
and whatever. And they could have totally kosher food. אלא מומר להכעיס.
Ela mumar l'hachis. Well, the assumption is... well I made it they
go for the ham over the beef then you could say they
like the ham better. But the way the גמרא Gemara is framing
it, I shouldn't have said it that way, because the way the
גמרא Gemara is framing it is you have two steaks and they're
the exact same, one is- one was שחט shachtet properly, the other
wasn't, and you said what do I need to bother with the
kosher one? I'll just, I might as well just eat the טריפה
treifa one. Right, right,
I shouldn't have described it that way. So that's considered a מומר
להכעיס, mumar l'hachis, or at least you know, we might want to
sort of say, it's interesting, is there a middle category? It's not
לתיאבון, l'teiavon, it's not להכעיס, l'hachis, it's just complete indifference, right? It's
like I complete- it doesn't mean anything to me, the מצוות. mitzvot.
Not like I'm trying to do it for spite, but I no
longer feel myself obligated by these laws of
כשרות. kashrut. So that's seen as enough to categorize him as like
חוץ לקהל. chutz l'kahal. Okay, obviously this, you know, how this plays
out in the modern era, you know, is radically different. But in
the time of the גמרא, Gemara, somebody who had a complete indifference
to whether to do a
מצוה mitzvah or עבירה aveirah when it was just as easy not
to, that's seen as somebody outside the community. So he says, אמר
להו, Amar lehu, זיל לא שבקו לי דאפרוקינך. zil lo shavku li
d'afrokinach. They have not- they are not letting me redeem you. Like
the rabbis here are basically not, you know, not, you know, I
want to redeem you but they're all making it impossible for me
to do so. Which is interesting, like why doesn't he say אפי'
הכי? afilu hachi? It's still a, you know, it's still a human
life. But of course, you know, there's challenging גמרות Gemarot about about
that, if it's somebody like a מין, min, you know, you don't
even try to save the life of a מין. min. So they're
categorizing him as a מין. min. So it's very interesting here this
other dynamic of who do we feel a responsibility towards, even when
it's ממש mamash an issue of a human life, okay? It all-
also is interesting that he needed the קל וחומר kal v'chomer because
again, you know, was it two or three times? Why do you
even need the קל וחומר? kal v'chomer? It's just an immediate application
of the rule, right? You redeem somebody. But maybe because... but maybe
his point was that he realized that there was going to be
these claims that... that you know that they're not totally פרום frum
or something and he was trying to set up that nevertheless we
need to redeem them. But in the end he did not feel
he was able to. So it's a sort of sad end to
the story. So now let's see another famous story here, which is
a ריש לקיש Reish Lakish story. Now that we're dealing so you
might have heard some of these types of stories before. Yes.
The top רש"י Rashi on תכלה? Tuchula? רש"י Rashi doesn't seem to
say that the חשש chashash is sexual abuse, does he? Yeah, you're
actually correct. רש"י Rashi does say רש"י Rashi just says that it
becomes you're right, acculturated. Yeah, yeah, yeah, they'll be assimilated, they'll lose
their Jewish
identity. I mean the גמרא Gemara had
תכלה Tuchula before about the issue about the kids being ממזרים mamzerim
or being claimed to be ממזרים. mamzerim. So you're right. I was
reading it in a particular way that it was about sexual abuse.
You're right, רש"י Rashi just reads it about that they'll lose their
Jewish identity. Okay,
which might by the way set it up easier for why the
Rabbis pushed back and the Rabbis were saying like they've already given
up their Jewish identity so you know but the anyway. Right. In
other words, if it were if it wasn't the case and it
was abuse they'd be more of an obligation on the community. Right.
Although it's strange since רש"י Rashi started by saying אומה שאוכלים בני
אדם Uma She'ochlin Bnei Adam and the גמרא Gemara says it's קטלא,
Ktala, it seems like we're dealing with an issue that it's not
just a concern about observance, right? The concern is we have a
heightened responsibility here because there's their life is at risk. Okay, let's
take a look now at the next story. ריש לקיש זבין נפשיה
ללודאי. Reish Lakish Zavin Nafshei L'Ludai. ריש לקיש Reish Lakish sold himself
to these לודאי. Ludai. Now תוספות Tosafot says or these gladiators. תוספות
Tosafot says, if you look at תוספות, Tosafot, קודם שחזר למוטב, Kodem
Shechazar Lemuto, where before that he became like a פרום frum guy.
Okay, this was when he was in his bandit, you know, days.
מסתמא לא היה מזלזל בעצמו כל כך. Mistama Lo Haya Mezalzel Be'atzmo
Kol Kach. You know, once he was, you know, שומר מצוות Shomer
Mitzvot and part of the rabbinic class and the whole thing we
don't imagine and a big rabbi, we don't imagine that he would
go sell himself off to the gladiators, okay? But this was in
his early history. The early stories of ריש לקיש. Reish Lakish. So,
שקל בהדיה חיותא וגילגלא. Shakal Bahadei Chiyusa Vegilgla.
He took with him a sack and a stone in the sack.
אמר גמירי, Amar Gmiri, I
we have a tradition, I know, היומא בתרא, Hayoma Batra, the last
day, the day that you're going to die, where you know, that
these לודים Ludim will put you to death or you know you're
going to die in the games or whatever it would be. כל
דבעי מינייהו עבדי ליה. Kol De'ba Minaihu Avdi Lei. Any you have
your you're given a last request, anything you ask of them, they'll
they'll allow you. Why? כי היכי דליכלו דמיה, Ki Heichi De'leichlu Adamei,
in order that they should be like exonerated from your from your
murder, from the fact that your blood is going to be spit.
So they feel, you know, what we'll do is we'll give him
the right to give any request so therefore we won't we won't
be held to blame for his murder or he won't hold it
against us. So so he was ready for this last request and
he knew he was going to be given. יומא בתרא, Yoma Batra,
his last day, אמרו ליה, amru lei, they said to him, מאי
ניחא לך? Mai Nicha Lach? What would you like to what what
would you like to be done for you? אמר להו, Amar lehu,
he said to them, בעינא דאקמטינכו, Be'ina Akmitinechu,
I want to tie you all up, ואותבינכו, Ve'osvinchu, and have you
sit down, וכל חד מינייכו אמחי חיותא ופלגא. Vekol chad minaikhu amchei
chiyusa upalga.
And I want to hit each of you one and a half
times with my
sack. Okay, now if he said I wanted to kill all of
you obviously they would not have granted that request. But this is
alright, big deal, this is a silly thing he wants to feel
like he's a big shot, he wants to slap each of us
one and a half times. Alright, we'll let him do it. Okay,
so קמטינהו, kamtinehu, he bound them up, ואותבינהו, ve'osvinhu, and he had
them sit down. וכל חד מינייכו, Vekol chad minaikhu, כד מחיא חד
חיותא, kad machyei chad chiyusa, and when he smacked them one time
with his sack, and his sack had a stone in it, right?
So, you know, it you know, it packed a wallop, right? So,
נפק נשמתיה. Nafak Nishmatei.
So, it could mean that they died, although Soncino translated this as
he faint they fainted, okay? They were stunned, they were paralyzed. Anyway,
one way or another he's going to escape, right? Because each time
he's smacking them, he's knocking them unconscious or killing them and now
he's going to escape. So and they can't do anything, they can't
change their mind because they're all bound up now. Alright. So חרקיניה
לשיניה, Charkinei Leshinei, so
one guy gritted his teeth at him. אמר ליה, Amar lei, אחוכא
קמחייכת בי? Achucha Kamachaychat bi? What, are you laughing at me? אכתי
פש לך גבאי פלגא דחיותא. Akati Pash Lach Gabai Palga Dechiyusa.
So, I still have another half a smack I can give you.
Alright. So קטלינהו כולהו, Katlinhu Kulu, and
now whether he stunned them originally, now after he was enraged because
it he interpreted this guy to be laughing at him, he wound
up and he killed all of them. נפק ואתא יתיב קאכיל ושאתי.
Nafak Ve'ata Yasiv Ke'achel Veshasei.
He went and he left and he was sitting down and eating
and drinking. He ran away from them, he was back home, everything
was good. I don't know why he wasn't afraid about reprisals, gets
back to the earlier גמרא. Gemara. Anyway, אמרה ליה ברתיה, amra lei
bartei, his daughter said to him, לא בעית מידי למיזגא עליה? Lo
Ba'yat Midi Lemizgal Lei? Don't you need something to recline upon? אמר
לה, Amar lah, he said to her, בתי, Bitti, כרסי כרי. Kareisi
Kari. My daughter, my stomach is my pillow. Okay, there are other
stories about ריש לקיש Reish Lakish and also רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
that they were like very fat, very huge, and so on. Okay,
so כי מנח נפשיה, Kimnach Nafshei, when he passed away, שבק קבא
דמוריקא. Shavak Kava Demurika. All he left behind in his name All
he had to his name when he died was a measure of
saffron. A what? A קב kav is a humongous amount, incredibly valuable.
Really? Yeah. And I know saffron is very valuable. Saffron is more
valuable by weight than gold. I mentioned that before. Even in antiquity,
seriously? Even there? In other words, in India, it's dirt cheap now.
Really? Yeah. Anyway, I don't know because the end of the, okay,
anyway, קרא אנפשיה, kara anafshei, he said about himself, ועזבו לאחרים חילם,
ve-azvu le-acherim cheilam, you know, they leave over their wealth to others.
So this could be read in two ways because the earlier part
of the פסוק pasuk is, if you read the פסוק pasuk in
context, here let me get it out. Oops.
The one thing that the what's-his-name Koren doesn't have is the תהלים
Tehillim in the back. Right,
the פסוק pasuk is, this is what you say at בית אבל,
beit avel, right? So it's right, right, right. It says like this.
It says, here, כי יראה חכמים ימותו יחד כסיל ובער יאבדו ועזבו
לאחרים חילם. ki yireh chachamim yamutu yachad kesil u-va'ar yovedu ve-azvu le-acherim
cheilam.
So it seems to be like that this is like a what
do you call? Like a like a tragedy. You know, what good
does it do? You know, other people inherit your wealth. You know,
what good does it do you? You're dead that you're leaving over
your wealth to others. So it seems like what he's saying, it's
hard to read what he's saying. It depends if you think this
קב kav of saffron is very valuable or it's saying that's all
he left. Okay, if you say it's all he left because that
sort of fits the other story about ריש לקיש Reish Lakish is
this, you know, he's this huge person, he's eating, he's drinking, whatever,
it's like, you know, eat, drink, and be merry for tomorrow we
die. Like why am I going to be stupid and leave over
my wealth for other people? I might as well spend it all
on myself right now. So that seems to be more fitting with
the idea, although I do understand your קשיא kashya about the value
of saffron. All right, anyway, let's take a look now at the
next case. משנה. Mishnah. Now we move from selling yourself and redeeming
people and redeeming captives to redeeming the land. So let's take a
look. המוכר את שדהו לעובדי כוכבים. ha-mocher et sadehu le-ovdei kochavim.
You sold your field to non-Jews. And this is a field in
ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. So we don't like that to be sold
because A, it takes the field out of the obligation of תרומות
ומעשרות terumot u-ma'asrot possibly. There's the מצוה mitzvah angle. And then there's
the, you know, societal aspect about we want to maintain this Jewish
presence in Israel. And it's clear in מסכת עבודה זרה Masechet Avodah
Zarah that we do not like selling land and slaves and animals
to non-Jews. You know, we want those are the things that establish
the presence in the land, certainly the land does. So anyway, you
went ahead and you did this. So what do you have to
do this? לוקח ומביא ממנו ביכורים מפני תיקון העולם. lokeiach u-meivi mimenu
bikkurim mipnei tikkun ha-olam. So there's two ways of reading, at least
two ways of reading this משנה. Mishnah. One way is we require
you to repurchase, this is the way רש״י Rashi reads it, we
require you to repurchase the fruit, at least the at least the
first of the fruit, so that you can then bring that as
ביכורים. bikkurim. So you sold your entire field to him. You now
have an obligation each year to go and to buy the first
fruit back from him and bring it as ביכורים. bikkurim. So לוקח
lokeiach is part of the תקנה. takanah. That's the way רש״י Rashi
reads it. The other way of reading it is
הלוקח מביא ממנו ביכורים. ha-lokeiach meivi mimenu bikkurim. If you purchased from
him, then you still have to bring that fruit as ביכורים. bikkurim.
You don't have an obligation to purchase, but if you do purchase
the fruit, we will still treat it as still has this obligation
of, maybe not a תרומות ומעשרות terumot u-ma'asrot obligation, that's interesting, we'll
talk about that, but at least we will treat it as a
ביכורים bikkurim obligation and you bring ביכורים bikkurim from fruit that you
purchase. So whether part of the תיקון עולם tikkun olam is to
obligate you to purchase or not is debated. Let's take a look
at the גמרא. Gemara. And now we get, this is where like
we get into these such central topics throughout ש״ס. Shas. אמר רבה
amar Rabbah says רבה, Rabbah, אף על פי שאין קניין לעובד כוכבים
בארץ ישראל להפקיע מידי מעשר, af al pi she-ein kinyan le-oved kochavim
be-eretz yisrael le-hafki'a midei ma'aser, even though a non-Jew owns land in
Israel, it does not change its קדושה kedushah status and the land
still has the קדושה kedushah that any grain grown is obligated in
תרומות ומעשרות. terumot u-ma'asrot. תרומות ומעשרות terumot u-ma'asrot won't be given because
the non-Jew, you know, it's in the non-Jew's ownership, the non-Jew owns
it. But let's say you bought the grain that grew in the
non-Jew's field. Right, this happens a lot in Israel, right? You go
ahead and you buy fruit from Jericho or something. Right? You buy
stuff that was grown in Israel by fields owned by non-Jews. Is
it obligated in תרומה ומעשר terumah u-ma'aser the fruit? The non-Jew won't
give it, but are you obligated if you buy that fruit? So
he says if a non-Jew owns land in Israel, it does not
change the status regarding
תרומות ומעשרות terumot u-ma'asrot שנאמר she-ne'emar כי לי הארץ ki li ha-aretz
for the land is mine, לי קדושת הארץ li kedushat ha-aretz the
קדושה kedushah of the land remains mine, no matter what happens to
it, my the divine presence or קדושה kedushah remains in the land.
אבל, aval, even though that's true that it doesn't change the
קדושה, kedushah, יש קניין לעובד כוכבים בארץ ישראל לחפור בה בורות שיחין
ומערות. yesh kinyan le-oved kochavim be-eretz yisrael lachpor bah borot sichin u-me'arot.
He totally owns He has absolute property rights. He doesn't only have
the rights to benefit from the land, he can change the landscape.
He can go ahead and build and destroy and dig ditches and
whatever he wants. He totally owns it as his property, okay, from
a דיני ממונות dinei mamonot perspective, but from a יורה דעה Yoreh
Deah perspective, from a קדושה kedusha perspective, he hasn't changed it one
whit. That's what רבא Rava says, okay, שנאמר, she'ne'emar, as the verse
says, השמים שמים להשם והארץ נתן לבני אדם. hashamayim shamayim l'Hashem v'ha'aretz
natan livnei adam. Okay, so when it comes into sense of ownership,
we own it and we can fully transfer ownership, but קדושה, kedusha,
that remains God's. That's רבא's Rava position. רבי אליעזר אומר, Rabbi Eliezer
omer, the exact opposite, אף על פי שיש קניין לעובדי כוכבים בארץ
ישראל להפקיע מידי מעשר. af al pi she'yesh kinyan l'ovdei kochavim b'Eretz
Yisrael l'hafki'a mi'yedei ma'aser. No, his presence affects the קדושה, kedusha, okay,
and it doesn't have an obligation of תרומות ומעשרות. terumot u'ma'asrot. להפקיע
מידי מעשר, L'hafki'a mi'yedei ma'aser, שנאמר דגנך ולא דגן עובדי כוכבים. she'ne'emar
degancha v'lo degan ovdei kochavim. Now this doesn't sound like a deep
sense that the land, the metaphysical status of the land has changed,
although that's normally the way we frame it. He, you know, his
presence is מפקיע, mafki'a, like, you know,
uproots the קדושה kedusha from a perspective of תרומות ומעשרות. terumot u'ma'asrot.
The פסוק pasuk he's looking at things like a more of a
technical point. It's your grain, when it grows in your land, is
it חייב chayav in תרומות ומעשרות, terumot u'ma'asrot, right? ראשית דגנך, Reshit
degancha, the first of your grain. If it grew when it was
owned by a non-Jew, then it's not obligated in תרומות ומעשרות. terumot
u'ma'asrot. So that sounds like a technical point, right? I mean, there's
other exemptions. Let's say it grew when it was הפקר, hefker, right?
Is it חייב chayav in תרומות ומעשרות? terumot u'ma'asrot? Let's say it
grew when it was הקדש. hekdesh. I am מקדיש makdish my field,
right, and the grain grew when it was הקדש. hekdesh. It also
might be exempt in תרומות ומעשרות. terumot u'ma'asrot. So these exemptions don't
necessarily prove that the land loses its קדושה, kedusha, right? It's just
like if a non-Jew was owning it when it came at the
critical moment of growth, then you're not חייב chayav in תרומות ומעשרות,
terumot u'ma'asrot, right? So it's interesting that it's how do you conceptualize
this position that when a non-Jew owns the land, the grain is
exempt. Do you see that fundamentally the land has lost קדושה, kedusha,
or do you think, no, it's a technical issue, if it was
owned by a non-Jew at the time that it grew, then it's
exempt. It could be a lot of reasons why it would be
exempt, this is one of them. Okay, but that's רבי אליעזר's Rabbi
Eliezer position, that if the land is owned by a non-Jew, stuff
that grows is exempt, שנאמר דגנך ולא דגן עובדי כוכבים. she'ne'emar degancha
v'lo degan ovdei kochavim. אבל אין קניין לעובדי כוכבים בארץ ישראל לחפור
בורות שיחין ומערות. Aval ein kinyan l'ovdei kochavim b'Eretz Yisrael lachpor borot
shichin u'mearot.
What he doesn't have is he does not have full property ownership.
He can benefit from it, it's sort of like a קניין פירות.
kinyan peirot. He can have, he have rights of use, right? But
you cannot make structural changes, right? If you like rented your apartment
or whatever, right? There's so many things you can do without getting
the permission of the management. Okay, you cannot make structural changes to
the land, you don't have full property ownership. שנאמר להשם הארץ, She'ne'emar
l'Hashem ha'aretz,
the land belongs to God, okay, and there he means as property
ownership. So this position basically says a non-Jew can never fully own
the land as property, although he does exempt it from תרומות ומעשרות.
terumot u'ma'asrot. Is that a concept of that he has uprooted the
קדושה kedusha or is it a technical point of he happened to
have owned it at the critical moment? It's not clear, but that
is the position that he does not fully own the land and
that the stuff that grows is exempt from תרומות ומעשרות. terumot u'ma'asrot.
Okay, now the גמרא's Gemara going to say, going to try to
flesh out this debate. במאי קמיפלגי? B'mai kamifligi? What does this debate
hinge on? מר סבר דגנך ולא דגן עובדי כוכבים. Mar savar degancha
v'lo degan ovdei kochavim. So one learns this exemption, your grain and
not the grain of non-Jews. I should mention that what is the
critical moment? The critical moment is when the grain gets to be
a third ripe. Okay, when it gets to be a third ripe,
that is considered to be the moment when it's חייב chayav in
תרומות ומעשרות. terumot u'ma'asrot. So who owns it at that moment, all
right? So if it's owned by a non-Jew at that moment, it
was not your grain, it was his grain, and therefore even if
you now buy it afterwards or buy it as it continues to
grow, it doesn't matter. A non-Jew was owning it at the critical
moment where it's defined as grain, and it remains exempt from תרומות
ומעשרות. terumot u'ma'asrot. That's one דרשה. drasha. ומר סבר, U'mar savar, the
other says that's not what the פסוק pasuk is coming to tell
you, it's coming to tell you something different. דגנך ולא דיגון עובדי
כוכבים. Degancha v'lo digun ovdei kochavim. The דיגון, digun,
the דיגון digun is considered the מירוח, miru'ach, which is the piling
it in a pile and smoothing it out. So there's actually two
critical stages of תרומות ומעשרות. terumot u'ma'asrot. One is when the grain
reaches a third, then it's considered to be obligated or exempt based
on the conditions. And even at that time though, you can eat
from it דרך עראי. derech arai. You know, you can if you
take תרומות ומעשרות terumot u'ma'asrot once it's a third ripe, it's חל,
chal, it takes effect. If you did it earlier, it's like lighting
שבת Shabbat candles on Thursday. You did it earlier, it didn't take
effect. Okay, but you could light שבת Shabbat candles once it's an
hour before sunset. It would take effect once it's a third ripe.
But you are still allowed to eat from it without taking תרומות
ומעשרות terumot u'ma'asrot if it's עראי, arai, if it's not like sitting
down for a meal. Like a snack. Once you actually winnow and
thresh it and put it... and smooth out the pile and that's
considered נירוח *niruach* or דיגון *digun*, then it's טבל tevel *tevel* and
you are חייב chayav מיתה *chayav misa* if you eat from it
without separating תרומות ומעשרות trumos u'maasros? *trumas umaisers*. Okay, that's stage number
two. So one learns the דרשה *drasha* is דגנך *dagancha* if a
non-Jew owns it when it becomes a third ripe, then you're exempt,
and the other one says no,
you're not exempt from that moment. The only moment that matters it
could grow in the hands of a Jew, in the hands of
a non-Jew, it's always חייב chayav *chayav*. The one thing that would
make it פטור *patur* is who is there when they're doing the
smoothing out of the pile. That's the final moment when it really
becomes fully like טבל tevel *tevel* and תרומות ומעשרות trumos u'maasros? *trumas
umaisers* must be taken and at that moment if that's being done
by a non-Jew, then you're exempt. So now you see by the
way that this idea is not necessarily back to the קדושה kedusha
*kedusha* of the land, right? There could be technical moments which technically
are critical moments which if a non-Jew was doing it or was
owning it at those moments, then that's an exemption. It
certainly that's true about the pile, it's already cut and harvested and
the whole thing. So it doesn't have to be conceptualized as affecting
the קדושה kedushah, *kedusha* of the land. It's just which is the
critical moment of ownership that defines whether or not you're חייב chayav
*chayav* or not. Yes. The לשון *lashon* of טבל tevel *tevel* is
בלול *balal* that is to say it's mixed up together. Let's say,
yeah, okay, I mean I don't know the etymology but let's say.
Okay,
so that's one שיטה *shittah* about do you make that דרשה *drasha*
about owning it at the time it becomes ripe. Now the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* says like this: אמר amar, רבא *Amar Rava*, says רבא
*Rava*, מנא אמינא לה *Mina amina lah*, where do I get this
idea from? That we've taught in a משנה Mishna. *Mishna* that it
is not exempt in תרומות ומעשרות trumos u'maasros. *trumas umaisros*. לקט שכחה
ופאה leket shikcha u'pe'ah. של עובד כוכבים חייבים במעשר *Leket shikcha u'peah
shel akum chayavin be'ma'aser*. If you have לקט שכחה ופאה leket shikcha
u'pe'ah. *leket shikcha u'peah* that a non-Jew, he's living in Israel, he
decides to go along with whatever everybody else is doing and he
lets the poor collect לקט שכחה ופאה leket shikcha u'pe'ah *leket shikcha
u'peah*, you still have to take מעשר maaser, *ma'aser* אלא אם כן
הפקיר *ela im ken hefkir* unless he really unless he renounces ownership
of it. Because now what does this mean? So let's see what
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* does to figure this out. היכי דמי *Heichi
dami*, what's the case? אילימא דישראל ולקטינהו עובד כוכבים *Ileima de'Yisrael ve'liktinhu
oved kochavim*, what does it mean it's the לקט שכחה *leket shikcha*
of non-Jews? So there's two ways of reading this. One way, which
was not the way I said initially, is the ישראל Yisrael, *Yisrael*
allows not only Jews but even non-Jews to collect the לקט שכחה
ופאה leket shikcha u'pe'ah *leket shikcha u'peah*. Right? Right, exactly. So the
non-Jew is the עני oni *ani*. So okay, so then it's exempt
from תרומות ומעשרות trumos u'maasros. *trumas umaisros* אלא אם כן הפקיר *ela
im ken hefkir* unless the ישראל *Yisrael* is מפקיר mafkir *mafkir* it.
So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says what does that mean? הא מפקיר
mafkir וקיימי *Ha mafkir vekaimi*, he already was מפקיר mafkir *mafkir* it,
he allowed the poor to collect. Why would it be exempt from
why and not exempt why would it be חייב chayav *chayav* in
תרומות ומעשרות trumos u'maasros *trumas umaisros* just cause the non-Jew collected it?
He already made it לקט שכחה ופאה leket shikcha u'pe'ah? *leket shikcha
u'peah*. לקט שכחה ופאה leket shikcha u'pe'ah *Leket shikcha u'peah* is exempt
from תרומות ומעשרות trumos u'maasros *trumas umaisros* because it's basically הפקר hefker
*hefker*. Okay? So why the fact that the non-Jew picked it up
would that change would that make it obligated and what does it
mean unless he's מפקיר mafkir *mafkir*, he was already מפקיר *mafkir*, the
ישראל *Yisrael*. So that can't be what it means. אלא לאו *Ela
lav*, must mean דעובד כוכבים *de'oved kochavim*, the non-Jew is leaving לקט
שכחה ופאה leket shikcha u'pe'ah. *leket shikcha u'peah* in his field ולקטינהו
ישראל *ve'liktinhu Yisrael* and the Jew collects it. Okay,
so why now if the non-Jew were to really מפקיר *mafkir* the
food and say, you know, מפקיר *mafkir* the grain, it's הפקר hefker
*hefker* anybody wants can take then it'd be exempt in תרומות ומעשרות
trumos u'maasros. *trumas umaisros*. הפקר hefker *Hefker* is exempt in תרומות ומעשרות
trumos u'maasros *trumas umaisros*. But he didn't מפקיר *mafkir* it. What did
he do? He said I'm leaving it as לקט שכחה ופאה *leket
shikcha u'peah*. There's only one problem, which is
you're not obligated in לקט שכחה ופאה *leket shikcha u'peah*—the grain isn't
obligated in לקט שכחה ופאה *leket shikcha u'peah* the way רבא *Rava*
reads this because a non-Jew owns the field, so there's no concept
of לקט שכחה ופאה *leket shikcha u'peah* by the grain. So therefore
the non-Jew thought he was operating within this he was trying to
do a really good thing, right? Go ahead and leave לקט שכחה
ופאה *leket shikcha u'peah* but halachically we're saying that's not the status
of the grain. It grew in the field of a non-Jew, it
doesn't have a status of לקט שכחה ופאה *leket shikcha u'peah*. So
if he's letting the Jew take it, it's basically like he gave
it to the Jew, but it never had a status of הפקר
hefker *hefker* because it never really was לקט שכחה ופאה *leket shikcha
u'peah*. הא אם מפקיר וקיימי *Ha im mafkir vekaimi*, so if he
actually is מפקיר *mafkir* it and says I'm מפקיר *mafkir* this corner
and anybody who wants can take it, then it's פטור *patur* in
לקט שכחה ופאה *leket shikcha u'peah*—it's פטור *patur* in מעשר maaser. *ma'aser*.
But if he's saying I'm leaving פאה pe'ah. *peah*, halachically it's not
פאה pe'ah *peah* because it's grown by in the field of a
non-Jew. So he's basically just giving it to whoever chooses to take
it; it's a מתנה *matana*. It's still חייב chayav *chayav* in תרומות
ומעשרות trumos u'maasros. *trumas umaisros*. Okay let's just read that, it says:
אלא לאו דעובד כוכבים ולקטינהו ישראל וטעמא דהפקיר *Ela lav de'oved kochavim
ve'liktinhu Yisrael veta'ama dehifkir*, the reason you would be exempt is only
in a case where he actually was מפקיר *mafkir* it. הא לא
lo, הפקיר חייבים *Ha lo hifkir chayavim*, what the משנה Mishna. *Mishna*
is telling you is that if he wasn't מפקיר *mafkir* it and
a Jew took it as פאה pe'ah *peah*, you'd have to take
תרומות ומעשרות trumos u'maasros *trumas umaisros* because it's not really פאה pe'ah,
*peah*. So you see that non-Jewish ownership does not change the status
of the land. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says: לא lo, *Lo*,
no, I don't want to read it that way, לעולם אימא לך
*le'olam eima lech*... עובדי כוכבים. ovdei kochavim, It was owned by a
Jew and the non-Jew was the one to collect it. So then
why do we say that it's חייב chayav, in תרומות ומעשרות? trumos
u'maasros, It's already פאה. pe'ah Why should it all of a sudden
be חייב chayav. in תרומות ומעשרות? trumos u'maasros, So the גמרא Gemara
says ותימא דהא מפקיר וקאי v'te'ameis ha'mafkir v'kaymi is already הפקר hefker
because it's already, oops, I don't know what that is, excuse me.
It's already הפקר hefker because it's already
לקט שכחה ופאה. ניחא דמפקיר אדעתא דישראל. Niha de'mafkiri adaita de'Yisrael. No,
no, no. When I left it here, so it undermines the generosity
of letting non-Jews gather this לקט שכחה ופאה. When I made it
לקט שכחה ופאה and renounced ownership, that was on the presumption that
a Jew would come and take it. The Jews are the ones
that I'm leaving לקט שכחה ופאה for. אדעתא דעובדי כוכבים מי מפקיר?
A'daita d'ovdei kochavim mi mafkviri? I, you know, non-Jews come into my
field, I'm not gonna stand guard and make sure that they don't
come. But fundamentally, right, I made it פאה pe'ah. for the Jews.
All right, so here's the way it's reading this משנה. mishna, I
made this thing פאה pe'ah for the Jews. A Jew takes it
with הפקר hefker because הפקר hefker. is anybody can come and take
it. Okay, that's the status of פאה, pe'ah. but supposed to be
collected by Jews. So if that all happened, they collect it from
הפקר hefker and it's exempt from תרומות ומעשרות. trumos u'maasros, If however
a non-Jew comes and takes it, well, basically I didn't really wasn't
intending him to be able to take it. It wasn't really הפקר
hefker for him. So in that type of a case, I mean
it's funny, it's like הפקר hefker for a certain class of people
and not other class of people, which gets discussed by בית הלל,
Beis Hillel, בית שמאי, Beis Shammai, הפקר לעניים hefker l'aniyim and so
on, using this as a model to מפקיר to a certain class.
But for him it wasn't הפקר. hefker. So even if I'm gonna
like let him take it, I really sort of... I'm seen as
like he's taking my property. It's not that it was הפקר hefker,
in that context, but okay, I'm not gonna do anything about it.
So in that type of a case, it still wasn't הפקר and
it's still חייב chayav in תרומות ומעשרות. Terumos u-Maasros And the only
way it'll be exempt is if I explicitly מפקיר it, that'll, you
know, to anybody who comes to take it, Jew or non-Jew. So
that's how we're now reading that משנה. mishna. Yes. Could you read
it a little bit more generously to the Jew and say that
like פאה pe'ah. in and of itself is by its nature meant
for Jews? Right. So whether or not I'm happy about non-Jews coming,
maybe I want them to come, but it's fundamentally not... Yeah, I
think that that is correct. Meaning, I think that the basic status
is... meaning it's an interesting question about how you read those like
דרכי שלום darkhei shalom that we give these things to non-Jews and,
you know, practice playing out. Because right, because the פסוק pasuk says
ואכלו אביוני עמך, v'achlu evyonei amecha, or you know, the פסוקים psukim
are clear. You know, the whole story by רות Ruth and בועז,
Boaz, you know, it says למה, lama, what is... why did you
notice... I forget the beginning of the פסוק, pasuk, anyway, להכירני ואנכי
נכריה, l'hakireni v'anochi nochriya, right?
So I'm a foreigner. Right, so how much was the presumption, how
much do, you know, can a גר תושב ger toshav eat from
לקט שכחה ופאה? Are they entitled? Is somebody that's not even a
גר תושב, ger toshav, are they entitled? Is somebody who's a real
נכרי, nochri, a real foreigner, are they entitled? So you're right, it
might have nothing to do with the will of the בעל הבית.
balabayas. It might be the הלכה halacha is לקט שכחה ופאה goes
to Jews, not to non-Jews. Right? I'm happy for a non-Jew to
take, but that's not fundamentally its status of לקט שכחה ופאה. So
vis-a-vis the non-Jew it's not הפקר and it's still חייב chayav in
תרומות ומעשרות Terumos u-Maasros, until I מפקיר it. Yes. Well how does
that play out in reality? I'm the עובדי כוכבים, I've taken what
you've left as פאה. Right. So now you have to... No, you're
not gonna take תרומות ומעשרות Terumos u-Maasros, because you're a non-Jew. But
if you now go in turn and sell that to Jacob who's
a Jew, Jacob has to take תרומות trumos ומעשרות. It's still טבל
because it never was in a status of הפקר. Right, but my
question is a little different. How about for you? I keep it,
I eat all of it. Do you have to factor that quantity
into your field and pay...? No, no. It's like some of my
grain burned. I just take תרומות trumos ומעשרות on the rest. On
the rest. Yeah, yeah, yeah. It's relevant vis-a-vis you sell it to
Jacob here, then he has to take תרומות trumos ומעשרות. So Jacob
would have to know in the marketplace that if he's buying from
a Gentile, he's gotta ask "where'd you get the grain from?" Right.
Okay, so that's how we're reading it. But as opposed to the
other reading which probably was a more פשט pshat reading, which it
was the non-Jew's field, I the Jew take it, it's still obligated
because it's not real פאה and it's not really real הפקר, it's
just pseudo-פאה. It's still obligated in תרומות ומעשרות unless he's really מפקיר
it. And that would have been evidence that stuff that grows in
a non-Jew's field is exempt from תרומות ומעשרות, that it's not really
פאה. Okay, but that's... but we've rejected that proof. Okay, so רבה
Rabbah tried to bring that as proof that it exempts from תרומות
ומעשרות, but we've rejected that proof. Yes. You're saying if a Jew
had originally taken it and he wouldn't have to take מעשר, right?
But if he bought it from a non-Jew, then he'd have to
pay מעשר. Correct. Right. Because then he's not taking it as an
עני collecting תרומות ומעשרות, right? It's a different... Well he's buying. Yeah,
exactly. It doesn't matter. He's not going into the field and taking
it in that role of... okay. So the גמרא Gemara says, okay,
תא שמע, ta shema,
let's come try to prove it again. ישראל שלקח שדה מעובד כוכבים,
Yisrael she'lakach sadei me'ovdei kochavim,
so a Jew buys a field from a non-Jew, עד שלא הביאה
שליש, ad she'lo hevi'a shelish, if the grain is not yet a
third ripened... And וחזר ומכרה לו משהביא שליש, ve-chazar u-mechara lo mishe-hevi
shelish,
so he bought it from the non-Jew before it was a third
ripened, he owned it for about two days when it hit that
key moment of becoming a third ripened, and then he sold it
back to the non-Jew. He owned it just long enough to make
the grain חייב chayav in תרומות and מעשרות. maasros. Okay? שכבר נתחייבה
she-kvar nischayva
because it was obligated when it was in the hands of a
ישראל, which makes it very clear that if it had reached a
third ripened in the hands of a non-Jew, it would be exempt.
So that's a very clear evidence for who was the other position?
רבי זירא? Rabbi Zeira? רב אלעזר? Rav Elazar? רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer.
So נתחייבה אם לא נתחייבה לא. nis-chayva im lo nis-chayva lo. So
this is pretty darn good evidence that owned by a non-Jew at
such a time of a third exemption. So הכא במאי עסקינן בסוריא.
hacha be-mai askinan be-Suryia.
We're not talking about in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael proper, we're talking
about סוריא, Suryia, which is lands conquered by דוד המלך, Dovid HaMelech,
and those lands are only rabbinically קדושת ארץ ישראל. kedushat Eretz Yisrael.
So there, a non-Jew who owns the land will exempt it from
תרומות and מעשרות maasros because that's not ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael proper.
דקסבר כיבוש יחיד לא שמה כיבוש de-kasavar kibush yachid lo shmei kibush
that the fact that דוד המלך Dovid HaMelech conquered it does not
give it real קדושת ארץ ישראל. kedushat Eretz Yisrael. It was considered
not a conquering of the whole nation for various reasons we're not
going into right now, and therefore it has only קדושה מדרבנן, kedusha
mi-derabbanan, and there when a non-Jew owns it, it exempts it. But
where that's not ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael proper. So again, that was
claimed to be very strong evidence for רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer's position,
but we limit it to be talking about סוריא. Suryia. תא שמע,
ta shma, come in here. ישראל ועובד כוכבים שלקחו שדה בשותפות. Yisrael
ve-oved kochavim she-lakchu sadeh be-shutafut.
So a Jew and a non-Jew own a field in partnership. טבל
וחולין מעורבין זה בזה דברי רבי. Tevel ve-chullin me-uravim zeh be-zeh, divrei
Rebbi. So רבי Rebbi says every piece of grain is half טבל
and half owned by the Jew and half חולין, chullin, the part
owned by the non-Jew. Okay, which by the way, before we talk
about how you'd solve such a case, shows you that the fact
that the non-Jew owned it meant that it's exempt. So this is
half owned by a Jew, half owned by a non-Jew, it's half
exempt, half חייב, hayyav it's half טבל and half exempt grain, everything
mixed together. That's what רבי Rebbi says. רבן שמעון בן גמליאל אומר
של עובד כוכבים פטור ושל ישראל חייב. Rabban Shimon Ben Gamliel omer
shel oved kochavim patur ve-shel Yisrael chayav. This is a question of
יש ברירה. yeish breirah. רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon Ben Gamliel
says look, at the end of the day, I split all the
grain with the non-Jew. So do you say each of us has
grain that's half and half, right? Or do you say since the
half you took was always the half that was yours and that
was the stuff that was exempt, and the half that I took
was always the half that was mine and that's the stuff that's
a hundred percent חייב. hayyav So that's a question of יש ברירה.
yeish breirah. When we split it up at the end, does it
allow us now to look retrospectively and say the grain you got
at the end, we will now say that that was always your
grain from the moment it was growing. Or do we say no,
it's not, it was always half and half and we just swapped
it or whatever, but when it actually grew it was half both
of ours. Okay, so that's an interesting question about how do you
treat the grain in terms of is the grain you took home
a hundred percent חייב or is it somehow fifty percent חייב and
then how would you deal with it. Okay, so the גמרא says
עד כאן לא פליגי אלא דמר סבר יש ברירה ומר סבר אין
ברירה. ad kan lo peligi ela de-mar savar yeish breirah u-mar savar
ein breirah. The only question is whether we say the grain you
took home was retrospectively always the one that was yours and therefore
it's a hundred percent חייב or do we say no, and essentially
it was half yours and you bought the other half, you swapped
the other half with the non-Jew, but anyway, it's always half and
half. Okay, and that's the debate. But nevertheless, אבל דכולי עלמא יש
קניין לעובד כוכבים בארץ ישראל להפקיע מיד מעשר. aval de-chulei alma yeish
kinyan le-oved kochavim be-Eretz Yisrael le-hafkiy mi-yad maaser. It's clear that everybody
holds that a non-Jew's ownership makes it exempt from תרומות and מעשרות.
maasros. That's pretty taken for granted in this משנה, pretty strong proof.
So the גמרא says הכא נמי בסוריא וקסבר כיבוש יחיד לא שמה
כיבוש. hacha nami be-Suryia ve-kasavar kibush yachid lo shmei kibush. So that's
going to be our back pocket answer. Any proof for רבי אליעזר
Rabbi Eliezer that, ah, you see the non-Jew exempts it, yeah yeah,
we're talking about סוריא. Suryia. We're not talking about ארץ ישראל Eretz
Yisrael proper. Okay, so that's going to be a way to get
out of any evidence. But you know, again, that's not פשט. pshat.
The simplest פשט pshat is that it's assuming non-Jewish ownership exempts. Okay,
now the גמרא continues. אמר רב חייא בר אבין תא שמע, Amar
Rav Chiya bar Avin ta shma, come in here. המוכר שדה לעובד
כוכבים לוקח, ha-mocher sadeh le-oved kochavim lokeiach, finally we're getting back, circling
back to our משנה. לוקח ומביא ביכורים מפני תיקון העולם. lokeiach u-meivi
bikurim mipnei tikkun ha-olam.
So we'll read this תוספות's Tosafos way, which makes it easier. If
you buy the fruit that were from the field sold to the
non-Jew, you have to bring from it ביכורים bikurim because of תיקון
העולם. tikkun ha-olam. So that sounds like מעיקר הדין, me-ikar ha-din, you
don't have to bring ביכורים. bikurim. It's really exempt from ביכורים, bikurim,
but because we don't want people selling their fields to the non-Jews,
we want to, or we don't want the non-Jew land to totally
be lost and people forget the sense of the Jewish presence in
that land, so we want to ensure that, you know, that it'll
retain its status of having קדושה kedushah. and we'll mandate you to
either buy the fruit, or if we don't mandate you to buy
the fruit, we'll tell you if you did buy the fruit, you
still have to bring it. Okay, but that sounds like מעיקר הדין,
me-ikar ha-din, what are we talking about? That it actually is exempt,
right? And this is a harder thing to say it's סוריא. Suryia.
You know why it's harder to say this is סוריא? Suryia? Because
here it's about תיקון העולם. tikkun ha-olam. Why would we only make
it תיקון העולם tikkun ha-olam in סוריא, Suryia, right? Presumably, what we
care about is ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. And it sounds like מעיקר
הדין me-ikar ha-din the fruit is exempt. So the גמרא says מדאורייתא
mid'Oraita לא, so מפני תיקון עולם mip'nei tikkun olam אין, in, because
of תיקון tikkun
yes, that's why we have to do it, מדאורייתא mid'Oraita לא, but
biblically it's not obligated. So אמר רב אשי, Amar Rav Ashi, שתי
תקנות הוו. shtei takanos havu. No no no, there were two תקנות.
takanos. Really, דאורייתא d'Oraita it's obligated. But what happened? מעיקר הוו מייתי
מדאורייתא. me-ikar havu meishi mid'Oraita.
Originally they sold their land and the הלכה halakhah was like רבה,
Rabbah, it had קדושה, kedushah. they would buy the fruit or if
they would buy the fruit they would bring it as ביכורים, Bikkurim,
and that would be דאורייתא. d'Oraita. But then כיוון דחזי דקמיקרי ומזבני,
kivun de-hazei de-kamikrei u-mezavnei, okay
but one minute then what happened was that people felt, hey it's
not a big deal to sell it to non-Jews. You know why
it's not a big deal? Because oh, if we don't sell it
to the non-Jews it's going, it's losing its קדושה. kedushah No, it
keeps its קדושה. kedushah. I'll tell you what, I'll even do a
nice thing, I'll buy the fruit and I'll bring it as ביכורים,
Bikkurim, it's not so terrible that I sold it to the non-Jews.
So the fact that I was able to still bring ביכורים Bikkurim
made it easier for me to sell it to the non-Jews. I
didn't feel what I was doing was so terrible. Okay, just keep
the קדושה kedushah. so to speak, it has its קדושה. kedushah So
that was מעיקר הדין me-ikar ha-din it had its קדושה. But then
it was too easy to sell it. So תקנו להו דלא אייתו.
takinu lehu de-lo ayisu. The Rabbis said we don't want you to
bring it from those who... sort of like the case of if
you're going to divorce your wife under these circumstances, if you're going
to sell yourself into slavery, you're not going to be able to
reverse it. You don't have a backdoor, you don't have an escape.
Okay, so you're going to sell your land, you're going to have
to, it's very consequential, don't bring תרומות ומעשרות from it, don't bring
ביכורים Bikkurim from it. Okay, that was תקנה takanah number one. But
then what happened? כיוון דחזי דמאן דלא סגי ליה מזבין וקמשתקע ביד
עובדי כוכבים. kivun de-hazei de-man de-lo sagi lei mazbin ve-kamishtakei be-yad ovdei
kokhavim. You know, sometimes it's very nice that you make things very
consequential and drastic results, it doesn't always correct behave- change behavior. Some
people don't have any choices. You're telling me nobody's going to redeem
me if I sell myself into slavery? But I don't have any
money, I don't have any choices, I'm going to go ahead and
do it anyway. And then you know, then nobody's going to redeem
me and then it's pretty terrible, right? But so that will happen,
right? That's the downside of these תקנות. takanos. You tell me don't
bring ביכורים Bikkurim and that's going to stop me from selling my
land? Excuse me, I don't have any choices. I'm going to go
ahead and sell my land anyway. Okay, so they saw that people-
it was not doing what it was intended to do. It didn't
change people's behavior. They were still selling their land, they had no
choice. And now ביכורים Bikkurim wasn't being brought from the land. So
it was like the worst of both worlds. So what did they
do? הדרו ותקינו להו דאייתו. hadaru ve-takinu lehu de-ayisu. They reversed the
original תקנה takanah that fine, we'll go back to the original situation.
And it still has קדושת ארץ ישראל, kedushas Eretz Yisrael, which is
what it should have been דאורייתא, d'Oraita, and you go ahead if
you did sell it, go
ahead buy back the fruit, bring ביכורים Bikkurim from it. Okay, so
again not at all פשט pshat because in the end of the
day what it's saying is that this תיקון עולם tikkun olam was
really just saying we're reversing it back to the דאורייתא d'Oraita situation,
right? Which is that it's still חייב in תרומות ומעשרות, still חייב
in ביכורים, Bikkurim, bring ביכורים. Bikkurim. But besides that it's not פשט
pshat and again the פשט pshat is that owned by a non-Jew
exempts it. What is really fascinating I think is this bigger theme
of תיקון עולם. tikkun olam. You know you try to fix something
here and you say well we're going to make something- and again
the very fact that a תיקון עולם tikkun olam could actually be
imposing a harsh rule because we think it fixes a deeper systemic
problem. We're not going to let you you know remarry your wife,
we're not going to let you be redeemed from slavery, we're not
going to let you bring ביכורים. Bikkurim. Sometimes that could that could
fix the problem and sometimes the the societal and economic realities are
so great that that's not going to do anything. And then you're
just going to be left with the negative consequences of that, right?
So it's very interesting that type of a תיקון עולם tikkun olam
dynamic that is going on here. Okay, so that is the end
of that of that סוגיא. sugya. A pre-critical critical ש"ס Shas סוגיא
sugya whether a non-Jew's ownership exempts the land from תרומות ומעשרות, clearly
all of the evidence is that it does. Okay, whether it does
it because conceptually it removes the קדושה or whether it does it
because of a technical point of דגנך ולא דגן עובד כוכבים. d'gancha
ve-lo d'gan oveid kokhavim. Nevertheless it's the- obviously the simple sense is
that it does- it does exempt. Now we turn to another very
central ש"ס Shas סוגיא sugya debate of רבי יוחנן Rebbi Yochanan and
ריש לקיש Reish Lakish which at least we'll get started on and
we'll continue over שבת. Shabbos. איתמר itmar was taught:
המוכר שדהו לפירות. ha-mokher sadehu le-peiros. I sell you my field for
its- what's it called? Is it usufruct? Is that the word? For
the right to benefit from it. I- you're not just a renter,
you actually own it, but you don't own it to basic as
as as it's all yours. You own it for the purpose of
getting the benefit from it, which basically means you can't go ahead
and make structural changes, it's still my property. Okay, but you own
it as a קניין פירות. kinyan peiros. You own the גוף לפירות.
guf le-peiros.
Okay so, רבי יוחנן Rebbi Yochanan אמר, so can you now you're
going to get the פירות peiros and and you have it not
because you bought futures in the land, because it was your land
for the פירות. peiros. Can you bring ביכורים Bikkurim from the land?
Can you say על האדמה אשר נתתה לי? al ha-adamah asher natata
li? Because in the end I still own the title to the
land. So רבי יוחנן Rebbi Yochanan אומר omer מביא וקורא. meivi u-korei.
You can bring ביכורים Bikkurim from that land... excuse me, רבי יוחנן
Rebbi Yochanan אומר omer מביא וקורא, meivi u-korei, you bring ביכורים Bikkurim
and you're able to say על האדמה אשר נתתה לי. al ha-adamah
asher natata li. Your קניין פירות kinyan peiros makes you enough, it
makes it enough you... ריש לקיש אומר מביא ואינו קורא, Reish Lakish
omer meivi v'eino korei, you bring ביכורים bikkurim cuz it has an
obligation of ביכורים, bikkurim, it grew in the land of ארץ ישראל
Eretz Yisrael owned by Jews, okay, but you do not say אדמה
אשר נתת לי. adamah asher natata li. רבי יוחנן אומר מביא וקורא
קניין פירות כקניין הגוף דמי. Rabbi Yochanan omer meivi v'korei kinyan peiros
k'kinyan haguf dami. If you owned the land for פירות, peiros, it's
like you own have title to the land itself. ריש לקיש אומר
מביא ואינו קורא קניין פירות לאו כקניין הגוף דמי. Reish Lakish omer
meivi v'eino korei kinyan peiros lav k'kinyan haguf dami. No, it's not
as if you're the owner of the land, okay, it's not enough
to give you title, to give you a pseudo title to the
land. I mean I have the real title, but your קניין פירות
kinyan peiros is not enough to even give you a pseudo title
according to ריש לקיש. Reish Lakish. מביא ואינו קורא. meivi v'eino korei.
So let's read at least one proof for this. קניין פירות לאו
כקניין הגוף דמי. kinyan peiros lav k'kinyan haguf dami. איתיבי רבי יוחנן
לריש לקיש. esaivi Rabbi Yochanan l'Reish Lakish. רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan asks ריש לקיש. Reish Lakish. ולביתך מלמד שאדם מביא
ביכורי אשתו וקורא. u'lveisecha melamed she'adam meivi bikkurei ishto v'korei. It says,
the פסוק pasuk says by ביכורים, bikkurim, what's the whole
פסוק? pasuk? ושמחת בכל הטוב אשר נתן לך ה' אלוהיך ולביתך. v'samachta
b'chol hatov asher nasan lecha Hashem Elokecha u'lveisecha. You'll rejoice in all
the good that God is giving you and to your household. Your
household understood to be your wife. So from here he says what
this tells you is that you are bringing the fruit of your
wife's fruit as well. Now what does that mean? A woman comes
into
the marriage, she retains title to her fields, and the husband has
a קניין פירות kinyan peiros and he gets the produce from the
fields. So now that's actually a תקנת דרבנן. takanas derabbanan. So how
do you read that in the פסוק? pasuk? But תוספות Tosafos says
well it might be that the rabbis made that תקנה takana but
they were just legislating something that already had been a deeply established
practice, that reality that a husband would basically take over, get the
rights of the produce from his wife's field. That was already a
societal reality in the time of the תורה. Torah. And therefore it's
ולביתך, u'lveisecha, you bring that fruit and for your household as well,
for your wife as well. So he's saying ah you see you
can bring fruit that you have a קניין פירות kinyan peiros in
and presumably say האדמה אשר נתת לי. ha'adamah asher natata li. So
that's a proof for רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan. But she retains title
the land? But you're still able to say האדמה אשר נתת לי.
ha'adamah asher natata li. מלמד שאדם מביא ביכורי אשתו וקורא. melamed she'adam
meivi bikkurei ishto v'korei. אמר ליה, amar lei, so ריש לקיש Reish
Lakish says back to him, no, שאני התם דכתיב ולביתך. shani hasam
d'chsiv u'lveisecha. That's a special הלכה halacha by ביכורים bikkurim that you're
allowed to do it. That's not a rule. That's just a special
הלכה halacha by ביכורים. bikkurim. איכא דאמרי ika d'amri and some say
that the proof went the other way. איתיבי ריש לקיש לרבי יוחנן.
esaivi Reish Lakish l'Rabbi Yochanan. ולביתך מלמד שאדם מביא ביכורי אשתו וקורא.
u'lveisecha melamed she'adam meivi bikkurei ishto v'korei. That you when by ביכורים
bikkurim you bring your wife's fruit. התם הוא דכתיב ולביתך, hasam hu
d'chsiv u'lveisecha, that's a special case cuz the תורה Torah says ולביתך,
u'lveisecha, אבל בעלמא לא. aval b'alma lo. Normally it wouldn't give you
title to the land just cuz you had a קניין פירות. kinyan
peiros. אמר ליה, amar lei, טעמא דידי נמי מהכא קאמינא. ta'ama d'idi
nami hacha kamina. Yeah, you think that's an exception? For me, that's
my source. That's my paradigm. Because the תורה Torah says that you
מביא וקורא, meivi v'korei, I don't read that as an exception, I
read that as telling me the rule. The rule is is that
you because you have the right to the fruit, it's like you
have title in the land. Okay, so we will stop here and
continue this very critical debate tomorrow.